In this video, I'm going to walk you
through the deformers that exist inside
of Unreal Engine. These are GPU
deformers, which means they're very
fast, very easy to work with, and we've
got a couple different ones to choose
from. Let's dive in. So, here I'm using
shot 80. It is a more involved shot with
a bunch of different characters. And
unlike most of the other examples I've
been filming so far and, you know,
showing you these different tools and
workflows, I'm not going to go into the
live control rigs. We totally could, but
in this case, I'm just going to use the
baked animation subsequence. I'm going
to jump right in here. We've got all of
our characters ready to go. And I'm just
going to grab an beta here. I'm also
going to add a camera cut track just so
I can get out of the camera view and go
find him over here.
And I'm going to show you how to add
deformers onto, you know, whether you
have a control rig or animation
sequence, it doesn't matter. What I'm
going to do is I just need to find a
skeletal mesh actor in my sequencer,
which we have here. So, for beta, so
here towards the beginning of the shot,
he's not so preoccupied. Uh, I'm going
to grab his character. I'm going to go
to add, and I'm going to add a control
rig, but I'm not going to add just like
a regular like body posing control rig.
I actually want to grab a deformer from
the control rig menu. Now you can scroll
around and you'll find some of them in
here. But if you also want to filter,
you can also hit this little filter
button and you can specify like I want
to find, for example, a deformer or
deformer utility. But if I hit the
little check marks for deformer, I now
have a little button that'll filter by
deformers. So that'll make it a little
bit quicker. So this will show some of
the ones we're going to cover today. I'm
going to show you first the sculpt
deformer. a sculpt deformer once I add
it on here will put this into my scene.
So right here we have CRD which stands
for control rig deformer sculpt
deformer. Twirl that open and we have a
few different pieces of it. Um if I make
sure that my uh you know my game mode
stuff is off. I need to back out and
turn off the lighting. There's a lot of
extra icons in the way. I also turn off
effects. That's going to get rid of some
of the spark Niagara elements. clear
things up a little bit. So, back to my
animation sequence. Um, once we add the
sculpt deformer, it's going to add this
little ball
around the character's waist. And the
sculpt deformer comes in three pieces.
We have the sculpt deformer, the handle,
and the mask. So, the sculpt deformer
itself, this is the thing we want to
move around. And this is what's going to
control kind of where our deformations
are living. So, I'm just going to place
this on his head for now. And I'll make
it a little bit smaller so you can
really localize the effect in just a
moment.
And then we also have the handle. Now
the handle is this little blue ball on
top. And this is the thing that's going
to actually make it fun. Off the bat,
you can see what we're doing, right? So
I can kind of pull this up. If I take
the sculpt deformer and make it larger,
you're going to see that it, you know,
it affects a lot more of his head. Grab
the handle again. Oops, that's not the
handle. This is the handle. If I could
grab it. Here we go. And there you go.
This is a sculpted deformer. It allows
you to just make little cosmetic changes
to a mesh. And what's really cool about
it is how fast it is, right? You can do
this on a metahuman. The really advanced
realistic characters. This works on
them, too.
So, if he gets, you know, hit in the
head by a robot, you can just punch his
head in. Very cartoony. Um, but this
works on any skeletal mesh character or
asset, period. Um, because it's
GPUbound, it's very fast, very
lightweight. You can do this. You can do
multiple of these. You can do all kinds
of cool stuff with them. Um, you can
also change the fall-off. So, if I go
back to the sculpt former itself, we
have some different attributes in the
anim.
For example, we have the fall-off, which
will adjust sort of how that handle is
going to propagate throughout the ball.
We also have the side fall-off, which is
sort of the outer bounds to feather the
change beyond the bounds of the circle
or the sphere. Um, things like that. We
have an aim mode, which is sort of uh
whether this thing is like pointing in
that direction. I can show you if I go
back to the sculpture former, we have
aim mode. So that kind of spins the
normal direction
of the deformer as a whole. So if you
can kind of keep what's happening here
in your mind, his head's like, you know,
boom, boom, boom, boom. He's kind of
doing like a headbang.
But if I switch the deformer back to no
aim mode, you can see that when I mess
with the handle, it's a little bit
different. Anyways, there's also the
weight, which is that if you have this
thing turned on like that, you can just
kind of deactivate the thing overall.
So, you just have it not active and then
active later. And you can do all kinds
of crazy stuff with this. You can have
the sculpt deformer, you know, you can
you can constrain it to stuff. You can
attach it to things. You can leave it
somewhere so that when a character's
hand comes into contact, things happen.
You can also specify, hey, you know,
don't affect the entire character. just
a fake, you know, mess with the head up
to the neck for example. And that's what
this is here. This mask bone picker via
space switcher. It uses spaces and uh
masking over here, bone masks to sort of
limit where this can affect things.
That's something that I'm covering in
YouTube videos on my channel. I've got
that in my classes. But, um, we've got
more deformers to go into. So, I'm going
to keep moving forward. Now, I can just
delete this deformer off the character.
Let's do another one. I'll take beta.
I'll add another control rig and this
time I'll filter by deformer again and
I'll grab a lattice. Now the lattice you
may have noticed in a previous shot that
was actually in when he grabs the door
and he smashes the door into the floor.
We get that slow motion moment. Um there
was a lattice on the door and this was
how that was done. So the deformer for
the lattice, same kind of thing. We have
the deformer as a whole. So, we have a
controller to be able to position the
whole thing and figure out where you
want it, which can be very, very handy
because you kind of want to set this
thing up. And then we have all the
individual points. And so, this is going
to do exactly what you'd probably
expect. It's going to warp and skew the
character based on uh, you know, where
they fall within the box. So, if I come
over here, if I just grab this, maybe
I'll grab this one. Um, if there's
nothing in that section, nothing really
gets affected. And if I go over here,
see there's the hand, there's the wrist.
And the crazy thing about this is like
this is a 3D deformer effect. And all
the animation still works,
right? So, we've got all this like weird
wiggly animation happening now. But it's
important to keep in mind, see how this
hand is being pulled and stretched like
crazy. The robot is not. The reason for
this, right? So they're the robots are
not being affected by all this because
the robots don't have the deformer
applied to them. This is applied only to
this one skeletal mesh. If I wanted this
to affect the robot, I could probably
copy paste this lattice onto the robot
or make a similar one. You I could I you
could add this lattice with the same
defformations onto different characters
and then you would get it on all of
them. But this is sort of a per
character control rig. So it it gives
you very granular control. Uh, I can
also mute it so I can kind of see before
and after. And it's important to keep in
mind that with a lattice, this is
definitely a later in the game thing.
You do this when you're kind of done
with animation because if I take the
lattice and move it around, I can kind
of move the whole character through it,
which is really interesting and weird.
Um, but that's why it's it's kind of
helpful to know, you know, where your
character's going to be and what the
animation is going to end up before you
deal with this. Because if I put this
here and start animating, the character
is going to move through it. So anyway,
you do the animation first, then you do
the lattice later, and you can see it
does not affect the robots. So that is a
lattice deformer. And then one more I
want to cover super super fast, and that
is if I go back to beta and I go to
control rig deformer, we have the camera
space lattice. Now, this is what I'm
just going to kind of glaze over, but we
have a camera space lattice, which is
down here at the feet. This one is
designed to be constrained to a camera.
So, if I go ahead and just say, hey,
constraint parent constraint camera. And
uh what I want to do is I want to get
rid of the offset. So, I can right click
on the constraint. I can turn off the
offset. Boop. So, now you can see that
it kind of moves with the camera as the
camera moves around. And if I look
through the camera,
I have this little uh this little
window. Now, the the scale is a little
bit off. I need to adjust for aspect
ratio and and things like that. So here
I have an aspect ratio and a field of
view slider that I can I can play with
to get the exact settings that I need.
But if I just kind of bump this up close
enough so that you can see it. But now
what I'm able to do is sort of take this
this lattice itself and adjust it. So
I'm going to grab my soft selection.
I'll grab some points here and I'll just
kind of I'll move it around. And so if I
want to get some squash and stretch and
just like, you know, smear frames
essentially, you can see that I'm now
able to sculpt the actual like rig from
this camera's perspective. And you can
see that it's a bit weird, right? He's
all warped and bizarre. And that is a 3D
effect that is actually happening to the
character based on that that sort of
projection, which is really interesting.
And so once again, that's only applying
to a single character. I'd need to do
the work and then apply this to other
rigs as well. But the deformers are
really, really cool. And the main one
that I am going to recommend that you
probably want to play with is if I get
rid of this, uh, I can just go to my
character, any character, and you're
going to just add the sculpt deformer.
That is probably the one you want to
mess with. It is the easiest one to get
the hang of and by far the most
satisfying most of the time anyways,
right? Because that's the one that's
giving you this really fun like cartoony
effect. Just keep in mind that you might
want to scale it up or down to localize
the effects. So, if you're trying to get
it to uh be some kind of fun like Looney
Tunes impact, you're going to want to
make it quite a bit smaller than it
comes in at
and then play with the handle to do all
the fun stuff. But yeah, between the
sculpt tool and the lattice, you've got
a lot of fun stuff to play with. So
enjoy.